Arthur Glowka Papers
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
Arthur Glowka Papers
1909 - 2013
NPkMC-224-258
24 Linear Feet
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
Marist College
Arthur Glowka was a US Naval aviator from 1952 - 1957 and later became a pilot for Eastern Airlines. Glowka was particularly concerned with protection of the environment. Glowka partcitpated in many environmental groups and movements to encourage policy regulation and change to protect the environment. He proved to be an effective citizen-scientist and found errors in various government and science articles and played a significant role in improving the water quality of the Sound for the wildlife in the water and humans surrounding it.
Scope and Content
The Glowka collection consists of assorted pictures, newspaper clippings, magazines and research concerning the environment and its protection. The collection also includes slides, videos, and maps, in addition to various artifacts providing a glimpse into Glowka’s personal life.
Acquisitions Information
The Arthur Glowka Papers were donated to Marist College by the Glowka family on March 25th 2013.
Historical Note
Arthur Glowka was born February 5, 1931, in New York City. In Syracuse, he attended New York College of Environmental Science and Forestry, where he graduated in 1952 with a degree in forestry. After college, from 1952 to 1957, Glowka was a U.S. naval aviator, and during this time he went on photoreconnaissance missions over the Middle East, North Africa, and Southern Europe. After his work in the navy, he went to New Orleans and resumed diving with his friend Al Warriner. Warriner was a Gulf Coast master diver, who had taught Glowka underwater drilling and blasting. Glowka then traveled to Brazil, where he met commercial divers Bob Ballinger and Joao Mandica. The three men became partners and Glowka’s skills vastly increased the production of their alluvial diamond and gold mining operation on the Tocatins River. In 1959 Arthur Glowka married Marion Stadler and in the same year he began flying for Eastern Airlines. In 1981 he belly-landed a B-727 with 72 passengers at John F. Kennedy Airport, no one was injured, as the plane skidded 3,000 feet to a stop on a runway. Glowka retired as a captain of Eastern Airlines in 1989.
Another major concern throughout Glowka’s life was the protection of the environment. Specifically, Glowka worked toward tougher water pollution control in regards to sewage plants in the Long Island Sound. He, along with six others, formed the Hudson River Fisherman’s Association, which would later serve as a model for the U.S. environmental movement. The Association resurrected the Federal Refuse Act of 1899 and continued their aggressive style of environmental activism, winning a series of legal battles, ultimately inspiring the nation to follow suit. The group continued their work and in 1986 evolved into the Hudson Riverkeeper, the watchdog organization dedicated to keeping New York’s water clean. Glowka continued his work as an environmental activist and remained involved in the Riverkeeper, the Hudson River Foundation, and the Long Island Taskforce. He also was active in the Soundkeeper, Soundwaters, and Hudson River Sloop Clearwater. Glowka was awarded the Feinstone Environmental Award in 1980 in recognition for his long and distinguished work as an environmental activist. Beyond participation in environmental groups, Glowka had a deep interest in the environmental well – being of the Long Island Sound. He proved to be an effective citizen-scientist and found errors in various government and science articles and played a significant role in improving the water quality of the Sound for the wildlife in the water and humans surrounding it.
Restrictions to Access
There are no restrictions on this collection
Arrangement of the Collection
Collection is arranged into fifteen series: 1) Advocacy, has three subseries, 2) Arthur Glowka: Personal Items and Writings, 3) Articles and Notes left in Books, 4) Chesapeake Bay: Science Article Clippings, 5) Connecticut, has three subseries, 6) Graphic Materials, has five subseries, 7) Long Island Sound, has three subseries, 8) Long Island Sound Study, has three subseries, 9) Marine Life, has three subseries, 10) Miscellaneous: Various Article Clippings, 11) New York, has two subseries, 12) Publications, has eleven subseries, 13) Videos, 14) Oversized Graphic Materials, has six subseries, and 15) Awards
- 1. Advocacy, 1921 - 2013; 1; Boxes: 1 - 5
  Series contains correspondence and associated information, article clippings, and materials on political action
  - Subseries 1.1: Correspondence and Associated Information, 1978 - 2011; 1.1; Box: 1
    - Grants Correspondence, 2001- 2008 (Folder 1, Box 1)
    - Environment Correspondence, 1990 - 2011 (Folder 2, Box 1)
    - Long Island Related Correspondence, 1998 - 2007 (Folder 3, Box 1)
    - Political Advocacy, 1978 - 2005 (Folder 4, Box 1)
    - Connecticut, 1985 - 2011 (Folder 5, Box 1)
    - NOAA (National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration), 1990 - 2005 (Folder 6, Box 1)
    - OWAA (Outdoor Writers Association of America), 2000 - 2011 (Folder 7, Box 1)
  - Subseries 1.2: Article Clippings, 1997 - 2013; 1.2; Boxes: 1 - 2
    - Science News Articles, 1999 - 2013 (Folder 8, Box 1)
    - Cheasapeake Bay, 1998 - 2001 (Folder 9, Box 1)
    - News Articles for Connecticut, 2003 - 2011 (Folder 10, Box 1)
    - New York City News Articles, 2006 (Folder 11, Box 1)
    - Political Fishing Article Clippings, 1997 - 2012 (Folder 12, Box 1)
    - Political News Article Clippings, 1998 - 2011 (Folder 13, Box 1)
    - EPA (Environmental Protection Agency) News Article Clippings, 1998 - 2011 (Folder 1, Box 2)
  - Subseries 1.3: Political Action, 1931 - 2012; 1.3; Boxes: 2 - 5
    - EPA (Environmental Protection Agency) Basic Information, 2006 (Folder 2, Box 2)
    - EPA (Environmental Protection Agency) Correspondence, 2005 - 2009 (Folder 3, Box 2)
    - EPA (Environmental Protection Agency) Performance Manual and Report, 2004 - 2009 (Folder 4, Box 2)
    - Government Accountablity Office, 2005 -2011 (Folder 5, Box 2)
    - OWAA (Outdoor Writers Association of America) Informal Notes and Papers, 2001 - 2012 (Folder 6, Box 2)
    - OWAA (Outdoor Writers Association of America) and Lobsters, undated (Folder 7, Box 2)
    - OWAA (Outdoor Writers Association of America) Formal Correspondence, 2004 (Folder 8, Box 2)
    - OWAA (Outdoor Writers Association of America) Formal Correspondence, 2005 (Folder 9, Box 2)
    - OWAA (Outdoor Writers Association of America) Formal Correspondence, 2006 (Folder 10, Box 2)
    - OWAA (Outdoor Writers Association of America) Formal Correspondence, 2008 (Folder 11, Box 2)
    - OWAA (Outdoor Writers Association of America) Formal Correspondence, 2009 (Folder 1, Box 3)
    - OWAA (Outdoor Writers Association of America) Formal Correspondence, 2010 (Folder 2, Box 3)
    - OWAA (Outdoor Writers Association of America) Formal Correspondence, 2011 (Folder 3, Box 3)
    - NEPA (National Environment Policy Act), 2004 - 2006 (Folder 4, Box 3)
    - Interstate Environment Commission, 2006 - 2008 (Folder 5, Box 3)
    - Interstate Environment Commission, 2009 - 2011 (Folder 6, Box 3)
    - National Government and the Environment, 1978 - 2005 (Folder 7, Box 3)
    - National Government Article Clippings, 1979 - 1999 (Folder 8, Box 3)
    - National Government Basic Legal Information, 2007 - 2011 (Folder 9, Box 3)
    - National Government Article Clippings, 1980's - 2009 (Folder 10, Box 3)
    - National Government and Courts, 2004 - 2009 (Folder 11, Box 3)
    - National Government Article Clippings, 2001 (Folder 1, Box 4)
    - National Government Article Clippings, 2003 (Folder 2, Box 4)
    - National Government Article Clippings, 2004 (Folder 3, Box 4)
    - National Government Article Clippings, 2005 (Folder 4, Box 4)
    - National Government Article Clippings, 2006 (Folder 5, Box 4)
    - National Government Article Clippings, 2007 (Folder 6, Box 4)
    - National Government Article Clippings, 2008 (Folder 7, Box 4)
    - National Government Article Clippings, 2009 (Folder 8, Box 4)
    - National Government Article Clippings, 2010 - 2011 (Folder 9, Box 4)
    - National Government Article Clippings, 2012 (Folder 10, Box 4)
    - Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, 1998 - 1999 (Folder 11, Box 4)
    - Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, 2000 (Folder 12, Box 4)
    - Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, 2001 (Folder 13, Box 4)
    - Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, 2002 (Folder 14, Box 4)
    - Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, 2003 (Folder 15, Box 4)
    - Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, 2004 - 2005 (Folder 16, Box 4)
    - Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, 2006 (Folder 17, Box 4)
    - Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, 2007 (Folder 18, Box 4)
    - Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, 2008 (Folder 19, Box 4)
    - Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, 2009 (Folder 20, Box 4)
    - Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, 2010 (Folder 21, Box 4)
    - Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, 2011 (Folder 22, Box 4)
    - Atlantic State Marine Fisheries Commission, 2012 (Folder 23, Box 4)
    - Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, undated (Folder 24, Box 4)
    - National Government Booklets, 2003 - 2004 (Folder 1, Box 5)
    - Whistle Blower, 2004 - 2010 (Folder 2, Box 5)
    - Long Island Sound Stewardship, 2003 - 2007 (Folder 3, Box 5)
    - Political Action, 1998 - 2011 (Folder 4, Box 5)
    - Personal Items, 1931 - 1965 (Folder 5, Box 5)
- 2. Arthur Glowka: Personal Items and Writings, 1936 - 2013; 2; Boxes: 5 - 6
  - Navy Articles, 1955 - 1965 (Folder 6, Box 5)
  - Pictures of Art Glowka, 1965 - 1974 (Folder 7, Box 5)
  - Environment action / political, 1961 - 1992 (Folder 8, Box 5)
  - Empire Forester, 1952 (Folder 9, Box 5)
  - Personal Documentation, 1967 - 2003 (Folder 10, Box 5)
  - Related Articles, 1950 - 2013 (Folder 11, Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1963 - 1995 (Folder 12, Box 5)
  - Diamond Activities, 1958 - 1959 (Folder 1, Box 6)
  - Awards, 1980 (Folder 2, Box 6)
  - Early Years, 1936 - 1948 (Folder 3, Box 6)
  - Department Love, 1955 (Folder 4, Box 6)
  - Aviation Pictures, 1954 - 1962 (Folder 5, Box 6)
  - Navy Pictures, undated (Folder 6, Box 6)
  - Articles written by Art Glowka, 1971 - 1981 (Folder 7, Box 6)
  - Articles in relation to Arthur Glowka, 1978 - 1981 (Folder 8, Box 6)
  - Articles written by Arthur Glowka, 1971 - 2006 (Folder 9, Box 6)
  - True Man Magazine - Arthur Glowka articles in magazine, 1959 (Folder 10, Box 6)
  - True Man Magazine - Arthur Glowka articles, 1950 (Folder 11, Box 6)
  - Sports Illustrated - Arthur Glowka articles in magazine, 1970 (Folder 12, Box 6)
- 3. Articles and Notes Left in Books, 1970 - 2012; 3; Box: 7
  - Notes and Info Found in Angler's Guide to Sharks of the Northeastern United States, 1970 - 1985 (Folder 1, Box 7)
  - Notes and Info Found in Angler's Guide to Sharks of the Northeastern United States, 1978 - 1998 (Folder 2, Box 7)
  - Information that came out of The Night crawlers Manual, undated (Folder 3, Box 7)
  - Airman's Odyssey by Antoine de Saint Exupery, 2012 (Folder 4, Box 7)
  - How Industry Manipulates Science and, 2002 (Folder 5, Box 7)
  - No Angle Left Unturned: Facts, 1973 - 2010 (Folder 6, Box 7)
  - The Earthworm Book: How to Raise and Use, 1979 - 2002 (Folder 7, Box 7)
  - About Lobsters, 1975 - 1995 (Folder 8, Box 7)
  - Facts About Night crawlers, 1977 (Folder 9, Box 7)
  - Our Stolen Future, 1996 (Folder 10, Box 7)
  - On Bullshit, 2005 (Folder 11, Box 7)
  - Marketing Myths That Are Killing Business, undated (Folder 12, Box 7)
  - Merde, 1999 - 2000 (Folder 13, Box 7)
  - Stamford 350 Years 1641 - 1991 (Folder 14, Box 7)
  - Articles found in Interstate Environmental Commission 2008 annual report, 1991 - 2009 (Folder 15, Box 7)
  - Articles found in Interstate Environmental Commission, 2009 (Folder 16, Box 7)
  - Chipmunks on the Doorstep, 1978 (Folder 17, Box 7)
  - Food in History, 1998 (Folder 18, Box 7)
  - How to Remember Jokes and 101 Drop Dead Jokes to Get Started, 1996 - 2004 (Folder 19, Box 7)
  - The Decline in Males, 1999 - 2003 (Folder 20, Box 7)
  - The Worst Case Survival Handbook, 1998 - 2000 (Folder 21, Box 7)
  - One Good Turn, undated (Folder 22, Box 7)
  - The Plain Reader, undated (Folder 23, Box 7)
- 4. Chesapeake Bay: Science Article Clippings, 1996 - 2011; 4; Boxes: 7 - 8
  - Scientific articles, 1999 - 2001 (Folder 24, Box 7)
  - GAO (U.S Government Accountability Office) and Chesapeake Bay correspondence, 2006 (Folder 25, Box 7)
  - News Articles, 1996 - 2012 (Folder 26, Box 7)
  - National Geographic, 2005 (Folder 1, Box 8)
  - Chesapeake Quarterly, 2004 - 2011 (Folder 2, Box 8)
  - Pennsylvania and Chesapeake Bay, 2007 - 2008 (Folder 3, Box 8)
  - Ecosystem or Environment, 1998 - 2009 (Folder 4, Box 8)
  - Water Quality, 2008 - 2011 (Folder 5, Box 8)
  - EPA (Environmental Protection Agency), 2003 - 2009 (Folder 6, Box 8)
- 5. Connecticut, 1937 - 2013; 5; Boxes: 8 - 9
  Series contains materials on Connecticut animals, politics, and research.
  - Subseries 5.1: Animals, 1988 - 2012; 5.1; Boxes: 8 - 9
    - Birds, 2001 - 2008 (Folder 7, Box 8)
    - Environment Correspondence, 1995 - 2010 (Folder 8, Box 8)
    - Fish, fishing, wildlife, 1998 - 2012 (Folder 9, Box 8)
    - A Study of Marine Recreational Fisheries, 2001 - 2002 (Folder 10, Box 8)
    - Shellfish Management Procedures For Southern New England Towns, 1988 (Folder 1, Box 9)
    - A Study of Marine Recreational Fisheries in Connecticut, 2004 - 2005 (Folder 2, Box 9)
    - A Study of Marine Recreational Fisheries in Connecticut, 2006 - 2007 (Folder 3, Box 9)
    - A Study of Marine Recreational Fisheries in Connecticut, 2007 - 2008 (Folder 4, Box 9)
    - Annual Report 2006 - Monitoring the Marine Environment of Long Island Sound, 2007 (Folder 5, Box 9)
  - Subseries 5.2: Politics, 2000 - 2011; 5.2; Box: 9
    - Legal / political action correspondence, 2006 - 2010 (Folder 6, Box 9)
    - Long Island Sound in Conecticut, 2000 - 2011 (Folder 7, Box 9)
    - Politics, 2009 - 2010 (Folder 8, Box 9)
    - Legal Action, 2003 (Folder 9, Box 9)
    - Notes, 2002 (Folder 10, Box 9)
  - Subseries 5.3: Research, 1937 - 2013; 5.3; Box: 9
    - Water Quality, 2006 - 2009 (Folder 1, Box 9)
    - Water Quality, 2009 - 2013 (Folder 2, Box 9)
    - Water Quality - Water Pollution Control Authority, 2009 - 2012 (Folder 3, Box 9)
    - Water Quality - Water Pollution Control Authority, 2009 - 2013 (Folder 4, Box 9)
    - Water Quality - state / city articles, 1999 - 2011 (Folder 5, Box 9)
    - EPA (Environmental Protection Agency), 2005 - 2012 (Folder 6, Box 9)
    - Research, 2005 - 2011 (Folder 7, Box 9)
    - Environment, 1998 - 2008 (Folder 8, Box 9)
    - Environment, 1937 - 2011 (Folder 9, Box 9)
    - Nitrogen, 2008 (Folder 10, Box 9)
- 6. Graphic Materials, 1974 - 2009; 6; Boxes: 10 - 15
  Series contains graphic materials of aquatic biomes, the environemnt, marine life, mussels, and miscellaneous
  - Subseries 6.1: Aquatic Biome, 1974 - 2009; 6.1; Boxes: 10 - 11
    - Miscellaneous, 2003 - 2009 (Folder 1, Box 10)
    - Fish pictures, undated (Folder 2, Box 10)
    - Fish Pictures, 1974 - 2006 (Folder 3, Box 10)
    - Bass - crabs and clams in stomach, undated (Folder 4, Box 10)
    - Porgies fat on back, undated (Folder 5, Box 10)
    - Blacks / Porgies / Striper / Blue, undated (Folder 6, Box 10)
    - Sturgeon Hudson, 1998 (Folder 7, Box 10)
    - Freddy Bass Sores Pix, 2002 (Folder 8, Box 10)
    - Fish stomachs fat on back, 1998 (Folder 9, Box 10)
    - Dead fish and insides, 2006 (Folder 10, Box 10)
    - Fish trap, undated (Folder 11, Box 10)
    - Eels Hudson, undated (Folder 12, Box 10)
    - Marine Life Picture Transparencies, undated (Folder 13, Box 10)
    - Foam Pictures, 2009 (Folder 14, Box 10)
    - Glowka's Boat Skinny Bluefish Bunker, undated (Folder 15, Box 10)
    - Bluefish blitz, undated (Folder 16, Box 10)
    - Westcott Cove Crepedula and Oysters, undated (Folder 1, Box 11)
    - Crepidula at Todds Point, undated (Folder 2, Box 11)
    - Crabs in Stomachs, undated (Folder 3, Box 11)
    - Crabs in Stomachs, undated (Folder 4, Box 11)
    - Terrestrial Environment, undated (Folder 5, Box 11)
    - Marine Environment, 2006 (Folder 6, Box 11)
    - Stomach / Bass, Blues, Fluke, 2003 (Folder 7, Box 11)
  - Subseries 6.2: Environment, 1997 - 2007; 6.2; Boxes: 11 - 12
    - Marsh Haloween, 1998 (Folder 8, Box 11)
    - Greenwich Grass Island, undated (Folder 9, Box 11)
    - Throgs Neck Buoys, undated (Folder 10, Box 11)
    - Tidal Rip, 2000 (Folder 11, Box 11)
    - Throgs Neck Bridge Tidal Stadium, undated (Folder 12, Box 11)
    - Haloween Grass End, 1998 (Folder 13, Box 11)
    - Tidal Rip end, 2002 (Folder 14, Box 11)
    - Pictures of Sewage Plant, undated (Folder 15, Box 11)
    - November Manhasset Bay, 2000 (Folder 16, Box 11)
    - Boats, undated (Folder 17, Box 11)
    - Float Pix Bridges, 2007 (Folder 18, Box 11)
    - Middle Bank James Van, undated (Folder 19, Box 11)
    - House and leaves, 1997 (Folder 20, Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous Pictures, undated (Folder 1, Box 12)
    - Richie Corvelle pots and boat, 2004 (Folder 2, Box 12)
    - November 2000 Glen Cove, undated (Folder 3, Box 12)
    - Tidal Flows September, undated (Folder 4, Box 12)
    - Beach Hurricane and Tidal Rift Pictures, 1999 (Folder 5, Box 12)
    - Leaf Pickup, undated (Folder 6, Box 12)
    - Duplicates, undated (Folder 7, Box 12)
  - Subseries 6.3: Marine Life, 6.3; Box: 12
    - Marion Porgies, undated (Folder 8, Box 12)
    - Burt / Paul Porgies Squid Bait Poor Fish Cleaning Pix, undated (Folder 9, Box 12)
    - Nick Black Fish Peter Weakfish, undated (Folder 10, Box 12)
    - Nick Striped Bass, undated (Folder 11, Box 12)
    - Nite Rainbow Trout, undated (Folder 12, Box 12)
    - Herring Dipping Miaaus Spring, 1980 (Folder 13, Box 12)
    - Menhaden Slides, undated (Folder 14, Box 12)
    - Dove / Sturgeon Pix, 1971 (Folder 15, Box 12)
    - Oceanic Beach Boat Clam Boat, undated (Folder 16, Box 12)
    - WT Clamming Flounder and Flounder Cleaning Trolling Horseshoe Crab Saltwater, undated (Folder 17, Box 12)
    - Clam Mussel Shots, undated (Folder 18, Box 12)
    - Eels Winter Summer, undated (Folder 19, Box 12)
    - Fighting Canaries, undated (Folder 20, Box 12)
    - Ruth Breasting Ducks, undated (Folder 21, Box 12)
    - Dead Fish Pix and Inter Neas, undated (Folder 22, Box 12)
  - Subseries 6.4: Mussels, 1998 - 2002; 6.4; Boxes: 13 - 14
    - Mussel Bed Lloyds Peanut Bunker Stomachs, 2002 (Folder 1, Box 13)
    - Mussels Norwalk, 2000 (Folder 2, Box 13)
    - Mussels Shelf - West Beach, 1999 (Folder 3, Box 13)
    - Mussels Pelham Bay, 1998 (Folder 4, Box 13)
    - Mussels - Sand Diggers, 1999 (Folder 5, Box 13)
    - Mussel Meats, 1999 (Folder 6, Box 13)
    - Mussels Lloyds, 1999 (Folder 7, Box 13)
    - Mussel Dolphin Cove, Stamford Harbor, 1998 (Folder 8, Box 13)
    - Blue Mussel Darier Boat Club, New Rochelle, Klondike, undated (Folder 9, Box 13)
    - Mussels - Penfield Reef, 2000 (Folder 10, Box 13)
    - Brill Mussels, undated (Folder 11, Box 13)
    - Piling Barnacles - City Island Blue Mussels, 1999 (Folder 12, Box 13)
    - Blue Mussels Holly Pond Canal, 1999 (Folder 13, Box 13)
    - Mussels April, 1998 (Folder 14, Box 13)
    - Mussels Stam Breakwall, 1998 (Folder 15, Box 13)
    - Blue Mussels, undated (Folder 16, Box 13)
    - Mussel Cove, 1998 (Folder 17, Box 13)
    - Pt Washington Mussels, undated (Folder 18, Box 13)
    - Sullivan - mussels alewives, undated (Folder 19, Box 13)
    - Mussels Yacht Haven Breakwater, undated (Folder 1, Box 14)
    - Mussels Yacht Halved Breakwater, undated (Folder 2, Box 14)
    - Mussels Rocks Parking Lot, undated (Folder 3, Box 14)
    - Mussels Playland Pond, 1998 (Folder 4, Box 14)
    - Mussel Cove Early November, 1998 (Folder 5, Box 14)
  - Subseries 6.5: Miscellaneous, 6.5; Boxes: 14 - 15
    - Long Island Sound Fishing Show #1, undated (Folder 6, Box 14)
    - Long Island Sound Fishing Show #2, undated (Folder 7, Box 14)
    - Complete Hudson River Show, undated (Folder 8, Box 14)
    - Fulton Fish Market, undated (Folder 9, Box 14)
    - Westway Trade, undated (Folder 10, Box 14)
    - Antique Outboard Motors, undated (Folder 11, Box 14)
    - Making Wire Line and Putting on More Spinning Spooler, undated (Folder 12, Box 14)
    - Lobstering - Peter and Rex fishing, undated (Folder 13, Box 14)
    - Gold Brazil, undated (Folder 14, Box 14)
    - Brazil General, undated (Folder 15, Box 14)
    - Brazil Nuts, undated (Folder 16, Box 14)
    - Water Skiing Amazon O/B motors, undated (Folder 1, Box 15)
    - Marion and Kreiger Paul S/B, undated (Folder 2, Box 15)
    - Environment, undated (Folder 3, Box 15)
    - Environment, undated (Folder 4, Box 15)
    - Freddy Boiler, undated (Folder 5, Box 15)
- 7. Long Island Sound, 1991 - 2012; 7; Boxes: 15 - 18
  Series contains marine science article clippings, science article clippings, and science miscellaneous.
  - Subseries 7.1: Marine Science Article Clippings, 1995 - 2009; 7.1; Boxes: 15 - 16
    - Marine Life, 1995 - 2008 (Folder 6, Box 15)
    - Marine Life, 2005 - 2009 (Folder 7, Box 15)
    - South Bay, 2007 (Folder 8, Box 15)
    - South Bay, 2008 - 2009 (Folder 9, Box 15)
    - Fishery and Fish, 2002 - 2003 (Folder 1, Box 16)
    - Eel grass, 2006 (Folder 2, Box 15)
    - Long Island Sound, Fish, and Fishing notes, 2007 - 2009 (Folder 3, Box 16)
  - Subseries 7.2: Science Article Clippings, 1991 - 2012; 7.2; Boxes: 16 - 17
    - Hypoxia, 1991 - 2011 (Folder 4, Box 16)
    - Hypoxia, 1991 - 2012 (Folder 5, Box 16)
    - Data - Long Island Sound, 1991 - 2012 (Folder 6, Box 16)
    - Data - Long Island Sound, 1991 - 2012 (Folder 7, Box 16)
    - Notes - Long Island Sound, 1991 - 2012 (Folder 8, Box 16)
    - Climate Change, 2004 - 2008 (Folder 1, Box 17)
    - Research Articles, 2001 - 2012 (Folder 2, Box 17)
    - Long Island Sound Articles, 1996 - 2010 (Folder 3, Box 17)
    - Pollution, 1991 (Folder 4, Box 17)
    - Ecosystem, 2002 - 2010 (Folder 5, Box 17)
    - Ecosystem, 2003 - 2012 (Folder 6, Box 17)
    - Biodiversity, 2009 (Folder 7, Box 17)
    - Science Articles, 1998 - 2007 (Folder 8, Box 17)
    - Science Articles, 1997 - 2010 (Folder 9, Box 17)
  - Subseries 7.3: Science Miscellaneous, 1994 - 2011; 7.3; Boxes: 17 - 18
    - Long Island Sound Correspondence, 1998 - 2011 (Folder 10, Box 17)
    - Long Island Sound Environment, 1995 - 2011 (Folder 1, Box 18)
    - Long Island Sound Environment, 1995 - 2011 (Folder 2, Box 18)
    - Nitrogen, 1995 - 2008 (Folder 3, Box 18)
    - Long Island Sound Science Projects, 1995 - 2008 (Folder 4, Box 18)
    - Water Quality, 1995 - 2011 (Folder 5, Box 18)
    - Water Quality, 1995 - 2008 (Folder 6, Box 18)
    - Water Quality, 1995 - 2011 (Folder 7, Box 18)
- 8. Long Island Sound Study, 1961 - 2013; 8; Boxes: 19 - 22
  Series contains committee papers, financials, and programs, plans, and reports.
  - Subseries 8.1: Committee Papers, 1961 - 2012; 8.1; Boxes: 19 - 20
    - Long Island Sound Plan, 1987 - 2011 (Folder 1, Box 19)
    - Long Island Sound Plan, 2009 - 2011 (Folder 2, Box 19)
    - Science and Technical Advisory committee, 2003 - 2010 (Folder 3, Box 19)
    - Long Island Sound Foundation, 2004 - 2008 (Folder 4, Box 19)
    - Management Committee, 2005 - 2012 (Folder 5, Box 19)
    - Long Island Sound Study Policy committee, 2010 (Folder 6, Box 19)
    - Science and Technical Advisory Committee, 2003 - 2012 (Folder 7, Box 19)
    - Management Committee, 2004 - 2012 (Folder 8, Box 19)
    - Citizens Advisory Committee, 2003 - 2013 (Folder 9, Box 19)